So I'd like you to come back with me
اريد منكم ان ترجعوا معي في الزمن&lt;br/&gt;
just for a few minutes
لعدة دقائق فقط
to a dark night in China,
لى ليلة مظلمة في الصين
the night I met my husband.
الليلة التي قابلت فيها زوجي
It was a city so long ago that it was still called
كانت في مدينة منذ زمن قديم لدرجة انها
Peking.
كانت تسمى بيبينج (بكين)
So I went to a party.
ذهبت الى حفلة
I sat down next to a stout, middle-aged man
وجلست بجانب رجل متين في منتصف عمره
with owl glasses and a bow tie,
يلبس نظارة شبيهة بالبومه وربطة عنق
and he turned out to be a Fulbright scholar,
واتضح انه من طلاب منحة "فولبرايت" الدراسية
there in China specifically to study
وهو في الصين خصيصا لدراسة
Sino-Soviet relations.
العلاقات الصينية - السوفيتيي
What a gift it was to the eager,
ويالها من هدية لي آنذاك
young foreign correspondent that I was then.
كمراسلة شابة متحمسة
I'd pump him for information,
سآخذ منه بعض المعلومات
I'm mentally scribbling notes
كنت اكتب بعض الملاحظات في ذهني
for the stories I plan to write.
للقصص التي انوي كتابتها
I talk to him for hours.
حادثته لساعات
Only months later,
وبعد شهور
I discover who he really was.
اكتشفت من هو في الحقيقه
He was the China representative
كان مندوب الصين
for the American Soybean Association.
لجمعية فول الصويا الامريكية
"I don't understand. Soybeans?
"لا أفهم. فول الصويا؟"
You told me you were a Fulbright scholar."
قلت لي انك من طلاب منحة "فولبرايت"
"Well, how long would you have talked to me
"لكم من الوقت كنتي ستتحدثين معي
if I told you we're in soybeans?"
لو قلت لك انني في مجال فول الصويا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I said, "You jerk."
فقلت له "ايها الحقير"
Only jerk wasn't the word I used.
لكن "حقير" لم تكن الكلمة التي استخدمتها
I said, "You could've gotten me fired."
قلت له "كان من الممكن ان تتسبب في طردي"
And he said, "Let's get married."
فقال "دعينا نتزوج"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Travel the world and have lots of kids."
"نجول العالم وننجب الكثير من الاطفال"
So we did.
وهذا ما فعلناه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And what an alive man Terence Bryan Foley
وكم كان تيرانس براين فولي
turned out to be.
رجلا مليئا بالحياة
He was a Chinese scholar
لقد كان طالبا في الصين
who later, in his 60s,
ولاحقا، في الستينات من عمره
got a Ph.D. in Chinese history.
حصل على شهادة الدكتوراة في التاريخ الصيني
He spoke six languages,
كان يتحدث ست لغات
he played 15 musical instruments,
ويعزف على ١٥ آلة موسيقية
he was a licensed pilot,
وكان شاعرا
he had once been a San Francisco cable car operator,
وقد عمل لفترة كسائق عربات كيبل سان فرانسيسكو
he was an expert in swine nutrition,
وكان خبيرا في تغذية الخنازير
dairy cattle, Dixieland jazz, film noir,
والماشيه، وجاز ديكسيلاند، وافلام الجرائم الهوليووديه
and we did travel the country, and the world,
وتجولنا في انحاء البلاد، وانحاء العالم
and we did have a lot of kids.
وأنجبنا العديد من الاطفال
We followed my job, and it seemed like
وتابعنا وظيفتي، وبدا لنا
there was nothing that we couldn't do.
انه ليس هناك شيء لانستطيع ان نفعله
So when we found the cancer,
لذا عندما اكتشفنا وجود السرطان
it doesn't seem strange to us at all
لم يكن غريبا
that without saying a word to each other,
اننا وبدون ان ننطق بشيء
we believed that,
اعتقدنا
if we were smart enough
انه اذا كنا اذكياء
and strong enough and brave enough,
وأقوياء وشجعان كفايه
and we worked hard enough,
وعملنا بجهد كافي
we could keep him from dying ever.
اننا نستطيع ان نمنعه من الموت أبدا
And for years, it seemed like we were succeeding.
ولمدة سنوات بدا وكأننا نجحنا
The surgeon emerged from the surgery.
خرج الجراح من العملية
What'd he say? He said what surgeons always say:
وماذا قال؟ قال ما يقوله الجراحون دائما
"We got it all."
"أخرجنا السرطان كله"
Then there was a setback when the pathologists
وبعدها جاءت نكسه عندما تفحص الاطباء
looked at the kidney cancer closely.
السرطان في الكليه عن قرب
It turned out to be a rare,
وتبين أنه نوع نادر
exceedingly aggressive type,
وعنيف جدا من السرطان
with a diagnosis that was almost universally fatal
وتشخيصه كان الموت باتفاق عالمي
in several weeks at most.
في اسبوعين على الأكثر
And yet, he did not die.
ولكنه لم يمت
Mysteriously, he lived on.
فقد استمر على قيد الحياة بشكل لايمكن تفسيرة
He coached Little League for our son.
وقام بتدريب فريق الناشئه الذي كان يلعب به ابننا
He built a playhouse for our daughter.
وبنى بيت مصغر لابنتنا
And meanwhile, I'm burying myself in the Internet
وأثناء ذلك كنت جاثية على الإنترنت
looking for specialists.
أبحث عن اخصائيين
I'm looking for a cure.
كنت أبحث عن علاج
So a year goes by
فمرت سنة
before the cancer, as cancers do,
قبل ان يرجع السرطان
reappears,
كما يفعل عادة
and with it comes another death sentence,
ومعه يأتي حكم اعدام آخر
this time nine months.
وهذه المره تسعة اشهر
So we try another treatment, aggressive, nasty.
فجربنا علاج آخر قوي وكريه
It makes him so sick, he has to quit it,
مما جعله مريضا جدا لدرجة انه اوقف
yet still he lives on.
ومع ذلك عاش
Then another year goes by.
وتمر سنة اخرى
Two years go by.
سنتين
More specialists.
والمزيد من الأخصائيين
We take the kids to Italy.
أخذنا الأطفال الى إيطاليا
We take the kids to Australia.
وأخذناهم الى استراليا
And then more years pass,
وتمر سنوات اخرى
and the cancer begins to grow.
ويبدأ السرطان بالنمو
This time, there's new treatments on the horizon.
لكن هذه المره، هناك علاجات جديدة بدأت تظهر بالأفق
They're exotic. They're experimental.
علاجات غريبة وتجريبية
They're going to attack the cancer in new ways.
ستهاجم المرض بطرق جديدة
So he enters a clinical trial, and it works.
فدخل في تجربة سريرية، ونجحت
The cancer begins to shrink,
وبدأ السرطان بالتقلص
and for the third time,
وللمرة الثالثة
we've dodged death.
تجنبنا الموت
So now I ask you,
لذا أنا اسألكم الآن
how do I feel
ماذا سيكون شعوري
when the time finally comes
عندما تحين ساعته
and there's another dark night,
في ليلة اخرى مظلمة
sometime between midnight and 2 a.m.?
بين منتصف الليل والساعة الثانيه صباحا؟
This time it's on the intensive care ward
هذه المرة في جناح العناية المركزة
when a twentysomething resident
عندما يخبرني مقيم في العشرينات من عمره
that I've never met before
لم ألتقي به من قبل
tells me that Terence is dying,
أن تيرانس يحتضر
perhaps tonight.
وربما يموت الليلة
So what do I say when he says,
فماذا أقول عندما يسألني
"What do you want me to do?"
"ماذا تريديني ان افعل؟"
There's another drug out there.
سيكون هناك علاج آخر
It's newer. It's more powerful.
أحدث. أكثر قوة
He started it just two weeks ago.
بدأ به منذ اسبوعين فقط
Perhaps there's still hope ahead.
ربما هناك أمل
So what do I say?
فماذا اقول؟
I say, "Keep him alive if you can."
أقول "ابقيه حيا اذا استطعت"
And Terence died six days later.
ومات تيرانس بعد ستة ايام
So we fought, we struggled, we triumphed.
لذا كافحنا، وناضلنا ونجحنا
It was an exhilarating fight,
وكان كفاح بهيج
and I'd repeat the fight today
وسأعيد هذا الكفاح
without a moment's hesitation.
بدون لحظة تردد
We fought together, we lived together.
حاربنا معا، وعشنا معا
It turned what could have been
وما كان من الممكن ان تكون اسوأ
seven of the grimmest years of our life
سبع سنوات في حياتنا
into seven of the most glorious.
اصبحت من أفضل سبع سنوات في حياتنا
It was also an expensive fight.
كما كان ايضا نضال مكلف
It was the kind of fight and the kind of choices
كان نضال وكانت خيارات من النوع الذي
that everyone here agrees
وباتفاق الجميع هنا
pump up the cost of end-of-life care,
تستهلك المخصصات المالية
and of healthcare for all of us.
والرعاية الصحية لنا جميعا
And for me, for us,
وبالنسبة لي، بالنسبة لنا
we pushed the fight right over the edge,
تغلبنا على ذلك النضال
and I never got the chance to say to him
ولم اتمكن من القول له
what I say to him now almost every day:
ما أقول له الآن كل يوم تقريبا
"Hey, buddy, it was a hell of a ride."
"يا رفيقي، كانت رحلة ممتعة"
We never got the chance to say goodbye.
لم نتمكن من أن نودع بعضنا
We never thought it was the end.
لم يخطر ببالنا أبدا أنها النهاية
We always had hope.
كان دائما لدينا أمل
So what do we make of all of this?
لذا ما الذي نستفيد منه في هذا كله؟
Being a journalist, after Terence died,
بعد موت تيرانس، ولكوني صحفية
I wrote a book, "The Cost Of Hope."
كتبت كتابا اسميته "قيمة الأمل"
I wrote it because I wanted to know
كتبته لأنني اردت ان اعرف
why I did what I did,
لماذا فعلت ما فعلته
why he did what he did,
ولماذا هو فعل ما فعله
why everyone around us did what they did.
ولماذا كل من حولنا فعلوا ما فعلوه
And what did I discover?
وماذا اكتشفت؟
Well, one of the things I discovered is that
احدى الأشياء التي اكتشفتها
experts think that one answer to
هي ان الخبراء يعتقدون أن احدى الأجوبه
what I did at the end was a piece of paper,
لمافعلته في النهاية هي قطعة ورقة
the advance directive,
وهي ورقة التوجيهات المسبقه
to help families get past the seemingly irrational choices.
لمساعدة العائلات لتخطي الخيارات التي يبدو انها غير عقلانية
Yet I had that piece of paper.
ومع ذلك كانت لدي هذه الورقة
We both did.
كلانا كانت لدينا
And they were readily available.
وكانت متوفره بسهوله
I had them right at hand.
كنت امسكها بيدي
Both of them said the same thing:
كلاهما، الورقة والخبراء قالوا نفس الشيء
Do nothing if there is no further hope.
لاتعملوا شيئا اذا لم يكن هناك أمل
I knew Terence's wishes
كنت اعرف رغبات تيرانس
as clearly and as surely as I knew my own.
كما اعرف رغباتي
Yet we never got to no further hope.
ولكننا لم نصل الى انعدام الأمل
Even with that clear-cut paper in our hands,
حتى مع وجود تلك الورقة الواضحه في ايدينا
we just kept redefining hope.
فقد ظلينا نعيد تعريفنا للأمل
I believed I could keep him from dying,
اعتقدت انني استطيع ان ابقيه حيا
and I'd be embarrassed to say that if I hadn't seen
ويحرجني أن أقول، انه لو لم أرى
so many people and have talked to so many people
واتحدث مع أشخاص كثيرين
who have felt exactly the same way.
شعروا بنفس شعوري
Right up until days before his death,
لأحسست وحتى ايام قبل وفاة
I felt strongly
بقوة
and powerfully, and, you might say, irrationally,
ويمكنكم ان تقولوا من غير منطق
that I could keep him from dying ever.
انني استطيع ان احفظه من الموت للأبد
Now, what do the experts call this?
والآن ماذا يطلق الخبراء على هذا الشعور؟
They say it's denial.
يقولون انه نكران
It's a strong word, isn't it?
انها كلمة قوية اليست كذلك؟
Yet I will tell you that denial
ومع ذلك سأقول لكم ان النكران
isn't even close to a strong enough word
ليست كلمة قوية كفاية
to describe what those of us
لوصف ما عانيناه أنا وهؤلاء
facing the death of our loved ones go through.
الذين يواجهون موت احبائهم
And I hear the medical professionals say,
واسمع الأطباء يقولون
"Well, we'd like to do such-and-such,
"بودنا ان نفعل كذا وكذا
but the family's in denial.
ولكن عائلة المريض في حالة نكران
The family won't listen to reason.
لن يسمعوا للمنطق
They're in denial.
انهم في حالة انكار
How can they insist on this treatment at the end?
كيف يصرون على هذا العلاج؟
It's so clear, yet they're in denial."
انه واضح جدا، ومع ذلك فهم في حالة انكار"
Now, I think this maybe isn't
والآن اعتقد انه ربما
a very useful way of thinking.
هذه ليست طريقة تفكير مفيدة
It's not just families either.
ليست العائلات فقط هم من في حالة انكار
The medical professionals too,
الأطباء
you out there, you're in denial too.
وانتم ايضا في حالة انكار
You want to help. You want to fix.
تريدون المساعدة. تريدون الإصلاح
You want to do.
تريدون ان تعملوا
You've succeeded in everything you've done,
نجحتوا في كل شيء عملتوه
and having a patient die,
ووجود مريض يحتضر
well, that must feel like failure.
لابد وأنه يبدو كفشل
I saw it firsthand.
شهدت ذلك بنفسي
Just days before Terence died,
قبل ايام من وفاة تيرانس
his oncologist said,
قال طبيب الأورام
"Tell Terence that better days are just ahead."
"قولي لتيرانس ان الأيام القادمة ستكون افضل"
Days before he died.
أيام فقط من وفاته
Yet Ira Byock,
ومع ذلك يقول ايرا بيوك
the director of palliative medicine at Dartmouth
مدير طب المسكنات في دارتموث
said, "You know, the best doctor in the world
افضل طبيب في العالم لم ينجح أبدا
has never succeeded in making anyone immortal."
في ان يجعل اي احد مخلدا"
So what the experts call "denial," I call "hope,"
لذا ما يطلق عليه الخبراء بـ "الإنكار" اطلق عليه انا "الأمل"
and I'd like to borrow a phrase
واود ان استعير عبارة
from my friends in software design.
من أصدقائي في مجال البرمجيات
You just redefine denial and hope,
فقط تعيد تعريف الإنكار والأمل
and it becomes a feature of being human.
فتصبح ميزه للبشر
It's not a bug.
فهي ليست خللا
It's a feature.
إنما ميزه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we need to think more constructively
لذا يجب علينا ان نفكر بطريقه بناءه
about this very common, very profound
بشأن هذا الإحساس البشري الشائع
and very powerful human emotion.
العميق، القوي
It's part of the human condition,
انه جزء من الحالة البشريه
and yet our system and our thinking
ومع ذلك نظامنا وتفكيرنا
isn't built to accommodate it.
ليست مبنيه على استيعابه
So Terence told me a story on that long-ago night,
اخبرني تيرانس قصة في ليلة منذ زمن بعيد
and I believed it.
وصدقت تلك القصة
Maybe I wanted to believe it.
ربما كنت أريد ان أصدقها
And during Terence's illness, I, we,
وخلال مرض تيرانس أنا أونحن
we wanted to believe the story
أردنا ان نصدق قصة أخرى
of our fight together too.
قصة كفاحنا معا
Giving up the fight -- for that's how it felt,
واستسلامنا -وهذا ما شعرنا به
it felt like giving up --
شعرنا انه استسلام
meant giving up not only his life
واستسلامنا يعني تخلينا ليس فقط عن حياته
but also our story,
بل وعن قصتنا
our story of us as fighters,
قصتنا كمكافحين
the story of us as invincible,
غير مقهورين
and for the doctors, the story of themselves
وبالنسبة للأطباء، قصتهم
as healers.
كمعالجين
So what do we need?
اذا ماذا نحتاج؟
Maybe we don't need a new piece of paper.
ربما ما نحتاجه ليست قطعة ورقه
Maybe we need a new story,
ربما نحتاج قصة جديدة
not a story about giving up the fight
قصة ليست عن الإستسلام
or of hopelessness,
او عن اليأس
but rather a story of victory and triumph,
ولكن قصة عن الفوز والانتصار
of a valiant battle and, eventually,
عن معركة باسله
a graceful retreat,
واخيرا عن انسحاب انيق
a story that acknowledges
قصة تقر انه
that not even the greatest general defeats every foe,
حتى اعظم لواء لايستطيع ان يهزم كل عدو
that no doctor has ever succeeded
انه لم ينجح اي طبيب
in making anyone immortal,
في ان يجعل احدا مخلد
and that no wife, no matter how hard she tried,
وانه ليس هناك زوجة مهما حاولت
has ever stopped even the bravest,
استطاعت ان تمنع زوجها من الموت
wittiest and most maddeningly lovable husband
مهما كان شجاعا وظريفا ومحبوبا
from dying when it was his time to go.
اذا جاء اجله
People did mention hospice,
ذكر لي الناس مأوى رعاية المحتضرين
but I wouldn't listen.
ولكنني لم اسمع لهم
Hospice was for people who were dying,
لأنه مكان للمحتضرين
and Terence wasn't dying.
وتيرانس لم يكن يحتضر
As a result, he spent just four days in hospice,
ونتيجة لذلك، امضى فقط اربعة ايام في مأوى رعاية المحتضرين
which I'm sure, as you all know,
وأنا متأكدة انها نتيجة
is a pretty typical outcome,
متوقعة كما تعرفون كلكم
and we never said goodbye
ولم نودع بعضنا ابدا
because we were unprepared for the end.
لأننا لم نكن مستعدين للنهاية
We have a noble path to curing the disease,
لدينا طريق نبيل لعلاج المرض
patients and doctors alike,
المرضى والأطباء سواء
but there doesn't seem to be
ولكن لايبدو انه يوجد
a noble path to dying.
طريق نبيل للموت
Dying is seen as failing,
ينظر للموت وكأنه فشل
and we had a heroic narrative
وكانت لدينا روايتنا البطولية
for fighting together,
لنضالنا معا
but we didn't have a heroic narrative for letting go.
ولكن لم يكن لدينا رواية بطوليه لوداعنا
So maybe we need a narrative
لذا ربما نحتاج لروايه تحكي
for acknowledging the end, and for saying goodbye,
ادراكنا للنهاية ولوداعنا
and maybe our new story will be
وربما تكون قصتنا الجديدة عن
about a hero's fight, and a hero's goodbye.
كفاح بطل ووداع بطل
Terence loved poetry,
كان تيرانس يحب الشعر
and the Greek poet Constantine Cavafy
والشاعر اليوناني كونستانتين كافافي
is one of my favorite poets.
هو احد الشعراء المفضلين لدي
So I'll give you a couple lines from him.
لذا سأقول لكم بعض من ابياته
This is a poem about Mark Antony.
هذه قصيده عن مارك انتوني
You know Mark Antony, the conquering hero,
كلكم تعرفون مارك انتوني، البطل القاهر
Cleopatra's guy?
حبيب كليوبترا؟
Actually, one of Cleopatra's guys.
في الحقيقه احد احباء كليوباترا
And he's been a pretty good general.
والذي كان لواء جيد
He's won all the fights,
فقد انتصر في كل المعارك
he's eluded all the people that are out to get him,
وراوغ كل الذين يلحقون به
and yet this time, finally,
وهذه المرة وأخيرا
he's come to the city of Alexandria
وصل الى الإسكندريه
and realized he's lost.
وادرك انه ضائع
The people are leaving. They're playing instruments.
الناس يرحلون، ويعزفون على الآلات الموسيقي
They're singing.
ويغنون
And suddenly he knows he's been defeated.
وفجأة عرف انه خسر
And he suddenly knows
وعرف فجأة ان الآلهه
he's been deserted by the gods,
قد نبذته
and it's time to let go.
وحان وقت الوداع وترك كل شيء
And the poet tells him what to do.
والشاعر يخبره ماذا يفعل
He tells him how to say a noble goodbye,
يخبره طريقة الوداع النبيل
a goodbye that's fit for a hero.
وداعا يليق بالأبطال
"As if long-prepared,
"كما لو انك تأهبت له طويلا
as if courageous,
كما انك شجاعا
as it becomes you
وكما هو لائق بك
who were worthy of such a city,
انت الذي هو جديرا بمدينة كهذه
approach the window with a firm step,
ادنوا من النافذة بخطوة ثابتة
and with emotion,
بعاطفة
but not with the entreaties
وليس باستعطاف
or the complaints of a coward,
او تذمر جبان
as a last enjoyment,
وكمتعة أخيرة
listen to the sounds,
استمع للأصوات
the exquisite instruments of the musical troops,
للآلات الموسيقية الرائعة للفرق العازفة
and bid her farewell,
وودعها
the Alexandria you are losing."
الاسكندرية التي ستخسرها"
That's a goodbye for a man who was larger than life,
هذا وداع رجل كان اكبر من الحياة
a goodbye for a man
وداع رجل
for whom anything,
كان كل شيء
well, almost anything,
تقريبا كل شيء
was possible,
بالنسبة له جائز
a goodbye for a man who kept hope alive.
وداع رجل ابقى الأمل حيا
And isn't that what we're missing?
أوليس هذا مانفتقده؟
How can we learn that people's decisions
كيف نتعلم ان القرارات التي يتخذها الناس
about their loved ones
في حق احبابهم
are often based strongly, powerfully,
هي غالبا مبنية وبشكل قوي
many times irrationally,
واحيانا كثيرة بشكل غير عقلاني
on the slimmest of hopes?
على بصيص أمل؟
The overwhelming presence of hope
وجود الأمل
isn't denial.
ليس إنكار
It's part of our DNA as humans,
انه جزء من تركيتنا الانسانية
and maybe it's time our healthcare system --
وربما حان الوقت لنظام الرعاية الصحية لدينا
doctors, patients, insurance companies, us,
من أطباء ومرضى وشركات تأمين ونحن ايضا
started accounting for the power of that hope.
بأن يضعوا قوة هذا الأمل في الحسبان
Hope isn't a bug.
الأمل ليس خلل
It's a feature.
انما هو ميزه
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)